Joshua's Tract Conservation and Historic Trust, Inc. Records 2007.0027
Archives & Special Collections at the Thomas J. Dodd Research Center, University of Connecticut Libraries
Joshua's Tract Conservation and Historic Trust, Inc. Records
[1675], 1963-2011
2007.0027
Archives & Special Collections at the Thomas J. Dodd Research Center, University of Connecticut Libraries
4.0 Linear feet
Joshua's Tract Conservation and Historic Trust is a membership organization formed in 1966 to receive gifts of money and land, or to buy land of historic, aesthetic, or scientific value, to be preserved for the benefit of future generations. Its region of concern includes the northeast Connecticut towns of Andover, Ashford, Chaplin, Columbia, Coventry, Franklin, Hampton, Lebanon, Mansfield, Scotland, Tolland, Willington, and Windham. Together with Joshua's Trust conservation restriction easements these properties create significant green corridors throughout the region, often abutting other agency's protected lands, watersheds, and trails. Records document the operations, activities and programs of the organization and include founding documents, by-laws, annual reports, meeting minutes, subject files, newsclippings, photographs and publications.
3 linear feet.
Joshua's Tract Conservation and Historic Trust, Inc.
Historical Note
In 1676 Joshua, son of Uncas and Sachem of the Mohegans, bequeathed his hunting grounds in the heart of eastern Connecticut to sixteen men of Norwich. This historic tract comprised the present towns of Windham, Mansfield, Chaplin, Scotland, and part of Hampton. Joshua's Trust, however, has extended its interest to Ashford, Columbia, Coventry, Lebanon and Willington, so that all towns of the Windham Region are included.
After three hundred years as a land of forest, farms, and villages, this ancient tract and countryside continues to draw development pressure as the population of people living in the Windham region increases. Joshua's Trust aims to guide and direct development so that open space is preserved as the needs of people, and those of future generations, are met.
Joshua's Tract Conservation and Historic Trust was organized and incorporated in 1966. It had grown out of the joint initiative of the Mansfield Historical Society and the Mansfield Conservation Commission. Interested persons from the surrounding area joined the effort. The Trust's initial financial assets totaled $1400 obtained from 56 founding contributors. The Trust acquired its first property, Bradley-Buchanan Woods, in 1970. Six more properties were secured during the 1970s including the historic Gurleyville Gristmill and miller's cottage, birthplace of Wilbur Cross who became one of Connecticut's Governors. The pace of acquisitions accelerated greatly during the 1980s when 18 tracts were added to the Trust's holdings and this acceleration continued through the 1990s. The Trust has also been actively working with landowners to establish conservation restrictions (easements). In 2007, Trust lands could be found in all of the Windham Region towns and in four neighboring towns - Andover, Franklin, Stafford and Tolland.
On September 8, 2005, the Trustees officially adopted the Land Trust Alliance's recommended Land Trust Standards and Practices as guidelines for Joshua's Trust operations. On January 12, 2006, the Trustees adopted a Strategic Plan that encourages the Trust's continual progress toward implementing the Land Trust Standards and Practices.
The Trust's logo is the replica signature mark made by the original Joshua. It represents a horse since he was one of the few Native Americans allowed by the Colonial British to own a horse. It is commonly referred to as "the critter".
Scope and Contents
The collection is comprised of administrative records, including founding documents, by-laws, annual reports, and annual meeting minutes, as well as subject files, newsclippings, photographs and publications that document the activities, operations, and programs of the organization since its establishment in 1966.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged into one series
Series I: Records ( [1675], 1963-2006 )
Related Material
Archives & Special Collections has a substantial collection of materials pertaining to Connecticut's flora, fauna and environment. For detailed information on these collections please contact the curator or ask at the reference desk.
Restrictions on Access
There are no access restrictions on this collection.
Acquisition Information
The collection was donated by Joshua's Trust in May 2006.
joshua's Tract Conservation and historic Trust.; Administrative Records.; Correspondence.; Fliers. [printed matter]; Historic preservation--Connecticut.; Land use--Connecticut.; Manuscripts.; Minutes.; Newsletters.; Newspapers.; Notes.; Pamphlets.; Photocopies.; Photographs.; Press releases.; Publications.; Speeches.
- Series I: Records, [1675], 1963-2011
  - Founding documents, 1963-1981
    - Pre-establishment, 1963-1966 (Box 1:, Folder 1)
    - Establishment, 1966-1968 (Box 1:, Folder 2)
    - Organizational history outlines, 1972-1981 (Box 1:, Folder 3)
  - Joshua's name, [1675], 1969, 1980, 1986, 1991 (Box 1:, Folder 4)
  - Annual reports, 1967-1976 (Box 1:, Folder 5)
  - Annual reports, 1976-1994 (Box 1:, Folder 6)
  - Annual reports, 1997-2000 (Box 1:, Folder 7)
  - Annual reports, 2001-2006 (Box 1:, Folder 8)
  - Annual reports, 2007-2010 (Box 3, Folder 48)
  - Annual meeting minutes, 1973-2005 (Box 1:, Folder 9)
  - Trustee meeting minutes, 1966-1970 (Box 1:, Folder 10)
  - Trustee meeting minutes, 1971-1974 (Box 1:, Folder 11)
  - Trustee meeting minutes, 1975-1977 (Box 1:, Folder 12)
  - Trustee meeting minutes, 1978-1980 (Box 1:, Folder 13)
  - Trustee meeting minutes, 1981-1983 (Box 1:, Folder 14)
  - Trustee meeting minutes, 1984-1986 (Box 1:, Folder 15)
  - Trustee meeting minutes, 1987-1989 (Box 1:, Folder 16)
  - Trustee meeting minutes, 1990-1991 (Box 1:, Folder 17)
  - Trustee meeting minutes, 1992-1993 (Box 1:, Folder 18)
  - Trustee meeting minutes, 1994-1995 (Box 1:, Folder 19)
  - Trustee meeting minutes, 1996-1997 (Box 1:, Folder 20)
  - Trustee meeting minutes, 1998-2000 (Box 1:, Folder 21)
  - Trustee meeting minutes, 2001-2002 (Box 1:, Folder 22)
  - Trustee meeting minutes, 2003-2005 (Box 1:, Folder 23)
  - Trustee meeting minutes, 2006-2011 (Box 3, Folder 49)
  - Trustee Handbook, 2005 (Box 1:, Folder 24)
  - Trustee Handbook, 2011 (Box 3, Folder 50)
  - Subject files, 1979-2002
    - Church Farm, 1988-1990 (Box 1:, Folder 25)
    - Church Farm, 1991-2001 (Box 1:, Folder 26)
    - Gurleyville Gristmill, 1979-1980 (Box 1:, Folder 27)
    - Gurleyville Gristmill, 1981-1982 (Box 1:, Folder 28)
    - Gurleyville Gristmill, 1983-1984 (Box 1:, Folder 29)
    - Gurleyville Gristmill, 1985 (Box 1:, Folder 30)
    - Gurleyville Gristmill, 1986-1987 (Box 1:, Folder 31)
    - Gurleyville Gristmill, 1988-1989 (Box 1:, Folder 32)
    - Gurleyville Gristmill, 1990-1991 (Box 1:, Folder 33)
    - Gurleyville Gristmill clippings, 1979-2002 (Box 1:, Folder 34)
  - Newsclippings, 1970-1981 (Box 1:, Folder 35)
  - Newsclippings, 1986-1991 (Box 1:, Folder 36)
  - Newsclippings, 1992-1997 (Box 1:, Folder 37)
  - Newsclippings, 1997-1998 (Box 1:, Folder 38)
  - Newsclippings, 2000-2006 (Box 1:, Folder 39)
  - Newsclippings, 2008-2011 (Box 3, Folder 51)
  - Newsclipping, various, 1970s-1980s (Box 3, Folder 53)
  - Newsclippings, various, 1970s-1980s (Box 3, Folder 54)
  - Photographs, 197?-2006
    - Ashford Oak, 1998 (Box 3)
    - Properties, Events and Programs, 197?-2006 (Box 1:, Folder 40)
  - Publications, 196?-2002
    - Brochures and pamplets, 196?-2010 (Box 1:, Folder 41)
    - Calendars, 1977-1980 (Box 1:, Folder 42)
    - Newsletters, 1969-1982 (Box 1:, Folder 43)
    - Newsletters, 1983-1989 (Box 1:, Folder 44)
    - Newsletters, 1990-1994 (Box 1:, Folder 45)
    - Newsletters, 1994-1999 (Box 1:, Folder 46)
    - Newsletters, 2000-2011 (Box 3, Folder 52)
    - Walk Books, 1991, 1999 (Box 1:, Folder 47)
    - Walk Book, 2005 (Box 3, Folder 55)
  - Photography Contests, Photographic Prints and Slides, 1973, 1992 (Box 2)